A Guide to the American Association of University Women, 1929-2011
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
American Association of University Women, 1929-2011
Special Collections, James Madison University
SC 5036
30 boxes (12.5 linear feet)
This collection consists of the important papers and other documents of the Harrisonburg Branch of the American Association of University Women (AAUW) spanning from 1929 to 2011. It also contains some papers from other Virginia branches of the AAUW, including Winchester, Staunton, Richmond.
American Association of University Women
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Lorrie Merrow first donated 2 record storage boxes and 1 poster on November 17, 2011. Tina Updike later donated 10 linear feet of materials consisting of documents and scrapbooks on December 6, 2011.
Biographical Information
The American Association of University Women was founded in 1882. The website states that the "AAUW advances equity for women and girls through advocacy, education, philanthropy, and research." This collection primarily covers the Harrisonburg branches actions and inner workings of the organization.
Scope and Content
The American Association of University Women (AAUW) Collection ranges in date from 1929 to 2011. Materials consist of papers as well as video, apparel, DVDs, CDs, scrapbooks, photos, and floppy disks. The collection focuses on the Harrisonburg Branch of the AAUW but there is information pertaining to the AAUW in VA and Nationwide. It is arranged in 12 series.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 12 series:
I: AAUW – The folders in this box contain materials that were transferred from their original folders or packaging to a new folder. No further sorting has been done, and any labeling has been transferred to the folder.
II: Bylaws- Ranging in date from 1967 to 1999.
III: Education- This contains many booklets that document women's struggle in the workforce as well as the AAUW's more internal education activities.
IV: Finance- This series contains information on every aspect of the AAUW's finances.
V: History- This contains newspaper articles and other historical moments of the AAUW as donated.
VI: Legal Documents and Activism- This series catalogs the range of actions that the AAUW took in support of various movements and issues. It also gives more information about the VA branch of the AAUW.
VII: Meeting Minutes- Range from 1929 to 2003.
VIII: Membership- This series catalogs every phase of membership from prospective to deceased. It also contains the forms, outreach materials, and policy sheets that would need to be filled out during that process. Mainly Harrisonburg Branch of the AAUW but there is some VA branch information.
IX: Publications-This series covers the publications, Graduate Woman, Outlook, The Link, Leader in Action, the AAUW Newsletter, The AAUW Program Guide, AAUW News, AAUW Journal, On Campus with Women, Action Alert, The Harrisonburg Branch Yearbook, The Inside Track, Virginia Vision, other VA Branch Newsletters, The AAUW Catalog, and other misc. publications.
X: Scrapbooks and Photo Albums- from 1929 to 1998.
XI: Special events and Conferences- from the 43rd Annual Convention to Convention of April 2006.
XII: Meeting Minutes- Range from 1929 to 2003.
Contents List
- AAUW
  - Cultural Rep. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Bound in a 3-Ring Binder (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Envelope to Christina Updike (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Miscellaneous I (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Miscellaneous II (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Share the Power, Share the Pride Marketing (Box-folder 1:6)
  - 1973-'75 M. Scherwitsky (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Association (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Publications (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Projects/Career Fair (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Community Rep. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Division (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Leadership (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Misc. Forms (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Forms of Pride (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Pres.'s Corresp. (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Programs (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Scholarships/Local (Box-folder 2:12)
- Bylaws
  - Bylaws 1999-2001 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Bylaws
  - Bylaws of VA 1997-1999 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Bylaws 1971-1987 (as donated/unsorted) (Bov-folder 3:4)
  - Branch Reports 1967-'79 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Branch Programs 1976 (Box:folder 3:6)
  - Branch Reports 1980s (Box:folder 3:7)
  - Harrisonburg Branch Officers 1985-'89 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Harrisonburg Branch Program 1985-'86 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Charter and Bylaws 1969 (Box 3)
  - Charter and Bylaws 1971 (Box 3)
  - Charter and Bylaws 1975 (Box 3)
  - Charter and Bylaws 1981 (Box 3)
  - Charter and Bylaws 1985 (Box 3)
  - Winchester Branch Directory 1970-'71 (Box 3)
  - Staunton Branch Directory 1973-'73 (Box 3)
  - Branch Leaders Handbook 1982 (Box 3)
  - AAUW Branch Report 1987-1989 (Box 3)
- Education
  - Educational Foundation Programs (as donated) (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Educational/Civil Liberties (as donated) (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Education Outreach (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Education (unsorted) (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Names Honored 1989-'90 (Box 4)
  - Fellowships and Grants 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - Names Honored 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - Delta Kappa Gamma Bulletin: Fall 1996 "Opportunities in Education" (Box 4)
  - Educational Foundation annual Report 1998 (Box 4)
  - Why so Few? Women in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (Box 4)
  - Gaining the Foothold: Women's Transitions Through Work and College (Box 4)
  - The Third Shift: Women Learning Online (Box 4)
  - Where the Girls Are: The Facts About Gender Equality in Education (Box 4)
  - Educational Foundation Directories for Fellowship, Grant, and Award Recipients 1997-2002 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Educational Foundation Fellowship Grants (as donated) (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Educational Publications (unsorted) (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Educational Misc. (unsorted) (Box-folder 5:4)
- Finance
  - Membership Finances (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Financial Statement: 1975-'86 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Jefferson National Bank (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Financial Summaries (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Invoices (Box-folder 6:5)
  - IRS Papers (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Letters and Reports to Branch Finance Officer (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Crestar (Box-folder 6:8)
  - AAUW Liability Insurance (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Branch Budgets: 1982, 1991-2001 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Branch Budgets: 1969-'70 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Finance Officers' Guide (Box 6)
  - Finance Officer Handbook 1995-'96 (Box 6)
  - Finance Officers' Guide 1998-'99 (Box 6)
  - Finance Officers' Guide 1999-2000 (Box 6)
  - Financial Guide for AAUW Treasurers (Box 6)
  - Deposits: 2004-2005 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Disbursements:2004-2005 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Sovran/National Bank Statements (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Disbursements: 2002-2003, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Dues and Remittance (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Financial Reports and Budgets 2000-2004 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - AAUW Treasurer: 1987-'88 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Fund Raisers (with receipts) (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Finance 1 (unsorted/as donated) (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Bound Ledgers (5) (Box 7)
  - National Bank (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Virginia National Bank (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Bank Statements I (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Bank Statements II (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Bank Statements III (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Box of Deposit Slips (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Receipts 20056-'07 (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Bills and Correspondence (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Miscellaneous Sales (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Treasurer's Reports: July 1990-1994 (Box-folder 9:5)
  - Various Checks and Deposit Slips (Box-folder 9:6)
  - Finance (unsorted) (Box:folder 10:1)
  - Deposit Records 1997-2003 (Box:folder 10:2)
  - Finance (unsorted) (Box:folder 10:3)
  - Aramark (Box:folder 10:4)
  - Brokerage Account Statement: Suntrust 2004,2005,2006 (Box:folder 10:5)
  - Bank Statements: Bank of America 2000-'04 (Box:folder 10:6)
  - Brokerage Account Statement: Suntrust 1999 - 2003 (Box:folder 10:7)
  - Brokerage Account Statement: Suntrust 2007 (Box:folder 10:8)
  - Receipts/Disbursements 1999 - 2001 (Box:folder 10:9)
  - Bank Statements: Bank of America 2004 - 2007 (Box:folder 10:10)
  - Manille Envelope- Wachovia Acct. CLOSED for Convention '06 (as donated) (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records (Box:folder 11:1)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records (Box:folder 11:2)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records (Box:folder 11:3)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records (Box:folder 11:4)
- History
  - History Information (Box-folder 12:1)
  - Newspaper Articles (Box-folder 12:2)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 12:3)
  - More Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 12:4)
- Legal Documents
  - AAUW 1987 Charter and Bylaws (Box:folder 13:1)
  - Virginia State Division Bylaws (Box:folder 13:2)
  - IFUW/International Federation of University Women (Box:folder 13:3)
  - Legislative Resolution (Box:folder 13:4)
  - ERA/ The Equal Rights Amendment (Box:folder 13:5)
  - Service/Political Activism (unsorted) (Box:folder 13:6)
  - Appt. Women to AAUW Boards at Local Level (Box:folder 13:7)
  - President's File (Box:folder 13:8)
  - Family/Women's Issues (Box:folder 13:9)
  - Legal Advocacy Fund (Box:folder 13:10)
  - Virginia Division Nominations (Box:folder 13:11)
  - AAUW Legislative Program and Candidacy (Box:folder 13:12)
  - Equity (as donated) (Box:folder 14:1)
  - Service Projects and Info (Box:folder 14:2)
  - 64th Annual Convention Registration Forms and Voting Delegates (Box:folder 14:3)
  - AAUW Office (Box:folder 14:4)
  - Peace and National Security (Box:folder 14:5)
  - AAUW Empowering Women: Achieving Change through National Advocacy (Box:folder 14:6)
  - A License for Bias: Sex Discrimination, Schools, and Title IX (Box 14)
  - 1989 AAUW Charter and Bylaws (Box 14)
  - The Military Budget: A Woman's Guide to Community Action (Box 14)
  - Report of the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Years 1976 "...To Form a More Perfect Union..." Justice for American Women (Box 14)
- Meeting Minutes
  - Random Years (unsorted) (Box:folder 15:1)
  - Board Meetings 1997-2003 (Box:folder 15:2)
  - Branch Minutes 1985-'88 (Box:folder 15:3)
  - Minutes 1973-'75, 1975-'77 (Box:folder 15:4)
  - Minutes 1954-1955 (Box:folder 15:5)
  - Minutes 1952-1954 (Box:folder 15:6)
  - Minutes 1938-1946 (Box:folder 15:7)
  - Minutes 1935-1937 (Box:folder 15:8)
  - Minutes 1933-1935 (Box:folder 15:9)
  - Minutes 1931-1933 (Box:folder 15:10)
  - Minutes 1929-1931 (Box:folder 15:11)
  - Minutes 1977-1979 (Box:folder 15:12)
  - Minutes 1985-1987 (Box:folder 15:13)
  - Minutes 1979-1982 (Box:folder 15:14)
  - Minutes 1984-1985 (Box:folder 15:15)
  - Minutes 1946-1951 (Box:folder 15:16)
- Membership
  - Perspective Members (Box:folder 16:1)
  - Membership Tool Kit (Box:folder 16:2)
  - Membership Outreach and Development (unsorted) (Box:folder 16:3)
  - Membership/Change Forms (Box:folder 16:4)
  - Policy Sheets (as donated) (Box:folder 16:5)
  - Dues and Policies (as donated) (Box:folder 16:6)
  - AAUW Directories (Box:folder 17:1)
  - Membership Records 1988-1989 (Box:folder 17:2)
  - Membership Records 1989-1990 (Box:folder 17:3)
  - Membership Records 1990-1991 (Box:folder 17:4)
  - Membership Records 1999-2000 (Box:folder 17:5)
  - Membership Records 2000-2001 (Box:folder 17:6)
  - Membership Records 2001-2002 (Box:folder 17:7)
  - Membership Records 2007-2008 (Box:folder 17:8)
  - Membership Records 2007-2008 (Box:folder 17:9)
  - Membership Records 2007-2008 (Box:folder 17:10)
  - Membership Records 2007-2008 (Box:folder 17:11)
  - Membership Records 2007-2008 (Box:folder 17:12)
  - Membership Records 2007-2008 (Box:folder 17:13)
  - Questionnaires and Forms (Box:folder 18:1)
  - Partial Membership Forms (Box:folder 18:2)
  - Membership Records (as donated) (Box:folder 18:3)
  - New Member and Renewal Reports (Box:folder 18:4)
  - Virginia Division Membership (as donated) (Box:folder 18:5)
  - AAUW Membership Officer Manual (Box:folder 18:6)
  - 1999 AAUW Membership Directory (Box 19)
- Publications
  - Graduate Women: Sept./Oct. 1979-May/June 1983 (Box-folder 20:1)
  - Outlook: January/February 1989, Volume 83 No. 1 – Spring/Summer 2010 Vol. 104 No. 2 (Box-folder 20:2)
  - The Lin: February 1996-Winter 1998 (Box-folder 21:1)
  - Leader In Action- Winter 1981-Spring 1988 (Box-folder 21:2)
  - Leader In Action-Fa;; 1993-Spring 1998 (Box-folder 21:3)
  - AAUW Newsletter: September 1971-May 1989 (Box-folder 21:4)
  - AAUW Program Guide: 1977-1981 (Box-folder 21:5)
  - AAUW News: March 1981-December 1989 (Box-folder 22:1)
  - AAUW News: January 1990-May 1994 (Box-folder 22:2)
  - Graduate Women: July/August 1983-September/October 1988 (Box 23)
  - AAUW Journal: January 1968-April 1977 (Box:folder 24:1)
  - On Campus With Women: Summer 1987-Fall 1992 (Box:folder 24:2)
  - Action Alert: October 1981-July 1999 (Box:folder 24:3)
  - Action Alert: April 1995-November 2003 (Box:folder 24:4)
  - "Other VA. Branch Newsletters" (as donated) (Box:folder 24:5)
  - Virginia Vision: Fall 1994-Spring 2003 (Box:folder 24:6)
  - Harrisonburg Branch Yearbook: 1976/77, 1985/86-1995/96 (Box:folder 25:1)
  - Harrisonburg Branch Yearbook: 1996/97-2010/11 (Box:folder 25:2)
  - Women Win The Vote (Box:folder 25:3)
  - Miscellaneous Publications (Box:folder 25:4)
  - "Va. Division" (as donated) (Box:folder 25:5)
  - AAUW Catalog (Box:folder 25:6)
  - Virginia Division Bulletin: Summer 1979-Spring 1984 (Box:folder 25:7)
  - Outlook: 1992-2011 (Box:folder 25:8)
  - The Inside Track: September 1991-March 2008, Winter 2011-'12 (Box-folder 26:1)
  - Virginia Vision: Fall 1997-Summer 2010 (Box-folder 26:2)
- Scrapbook and Photo Albums
  - Photo of AAUW National Board of Directors 1980 (Box 27)
  - 2/26/05 Crown Prints (Box 27)
  - Photo Album- Middle School Girls "Science, Math, and Technology Career Fair" JMU (Box 27)
  - Photo Album- AAUW 1981-1998 (Box 27)
  - Scrapbook-AAUW 50-51 (Box 27)
  - Scrapbook-AAUW Harrisonburg Branch: A Brief History of Branch activities from 1929-1947 (Box 27)
  - Scrapbook-AAUW 1977-1985 (Box 27)
  - Scrapbook-AAUW 1955-1975 (Box 27)
- Special Events and Conferences
  - Misc. Flyers and forms from various events (Box-folder 28:1)
  - AAUW Capitol Hill Day (Box-folder 28:2)
  - 1989 Virginia Division Convention (Box-folder 28:3)
  - 63rd Annual Convention (Box-folder 28:4)
  - 64th Annual Convention (Box-folder 28:5)
  - Misc. Convention Information (Box-folder 28:6)
  - 43rd Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 44th Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 52nd Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 53rd Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 54th Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 56th Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 58th Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 59th Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 60th Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 61st Annual Convention (Box 28)
  - 63nd Annual Convention (Box 27)
  - Maryland and Virginia Division Convention (Box 27)
  - 50th Anniversary Convention (Box 27)
  - 35th Biennial Convention (Box 27)
  - Preparing for the 21st Century: Who Will Shape Society's Agenda (Box 27)
  - 64th Annual Convention (Box:folder 29:1)
  - 64th Annual Convention Registration (Box:folder 29:2)
  - 68th Annual Convention (Box:folder 29:3)
  - 69th Annual Convention (Box:folder 29:4)
  - 71st Annual Convention (Box:folder 29:5)
  - 72nd Annual Convention (Box:folder 29:6)
  - 81st Annual Convention (Box:folder 29:7)
  - South Atlantic Regional Conference (Box:folder 29:8)
  - AAUW Week (Box:folder 29:9)
  - Convention April 2006 (unsorted/as donated) (Box:folder 29:10)
  - Special Events Misc. (unsorted) (Box:folder 29:11)
  - 73rd Annual Convention (Box 29)
  - 74th Annual Convention (Box 29)
- Miscellaneous
  - AAUW Misc. (Box:folder 30:1)
  - AAUW and non AAUW Ephemera (Box:folder 30:2)
  - Stationary/note cards. logos, slogans etc. (Box:folder 30:3)
  - Awards/Prizes (Box:folder 30:4)
  - 5-star (Box:folder 30:5)
  - 1982-1983 Public Information Awards Competition entry (Box:folder 30:6)
  - Memos and Notes (Box:folder 30:7)
  - "Record of My AAUW Membership" (Box:folder 30:8)
  - AAUW Publicity (Box:folder 30:9)
  - Mementoes (Box:folder 30:10)
  - Board Agenda and Minutes (Box:folder 30:11)
  - Branch Policy (Box:folder 30:12)
  - Budget/Finances (Box:folder 30:13)
  - Legal Advocacy Fund (Box:folder 30:14)
  - Membership (Box:folder 30:15)
  - "Diversity Tool Kit" (Box:folder 30:16)
  - AAUW Topic Guides 1981-1983 (Box:folder 30:15)
  - T-Shirt (Box:folder 30:16)
  - "1973 Tool Catalog" (Box 30)
  - AAUW Topic Guide for 1975-1977 (Box 30)
  - 1973 Tool Catalog (Box 30)
  - The 1960-1970 Decade of the Virginia Division of the AAUW (Box 30)
  - Reel of AAUW Public Service Announcements (Box 30)
  - DVD of AAUW Leadership Development (Box 30)
  - Baggie of 8 Computer Disks with Documents (Box 30)
  - Woodblock (Box 30)
  - Pin (Box 30)
  - AAUW Resource DC (Box 30)
  - CD - Keys to the Future: A Member Get a Member Campaign (Box 30)